A Guide to the John A. Ferrell Papers FA049
Rockefeller Archive Center
John A. Ferrell papers
1910-1944
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson)
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
Rockefeller Foundation
FA049
0.76 Cubic Feet 2 document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
John Atkinson Ferrell was born in Clinton, North Carolina, in December 1880. He received a B.S. from the University of North Carolina in 1902, an M.D. in 1907, and a Dr.P.H. from Johns Hopkins University in 1919.
From 1902-1905 Dr. Ferrell taught school and was County Superintendent of Schools in Sampson County, North Carolina. In 1907 he became County Superintendent of Health there. From 1910-1913 Dr. Ferrell was associated with the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission and was State Director for North Carolina. In 1914 Dr. Ferrell became Associate Director of the International Health Division of The Rockefeller Foundation and served in that capacity until his retirement in 1944. Dr. Ferrell then became Medical Director of the Markle Foundation from 1944-1946. He was also Executive Secretary of the North Carolina Medical Care Commission from 1946-1957.
Dr. Ferrell was a member of the American Medical Association, the Southern Medical Association, the National Malaria Committee of which he was Chairman in 1924, the Medical Society of the State of North Carolina for which he was Secretary from 1911-1914, the Medical Society of Wake County, North Carolina, the American Public Health Association of which he was President in 1933 and Chairman of the Board from 1935-1939. He was an honorary life member of the Conference of State and Provincial Health Authorities of North America and the Canadian Public Health Association.
Dr. Ferrell's publications include: "Medical Inspection of Schools and School Children," 1912; "Careers in Public Health," 1923; "Trends in Preventative Medicine," 1923; "Malaria of the South," 1924; "Health in Relation to Citizenship," 1924; and "Survey of Provincial and State Organizations," 1927.
Dr. Ferrell died in 1965.
Scope and Contents
Almost all of the material included in the collection is administrative and is indicative of trends and overviews as the result of a large amount of statistics included here. The collection briefly sketches Dr. Ferrell's association with the International Health Division of The Rockefeller Foundation.
Important subjects in this collection include hookworm projects and statistics, statistics and health projects, sanitary engineering, and nutrition.
Arrangement
The John A. Ferrell collection is divided into four sections: a desk book, a compilation of statistics, diary notes, and photographs. They are roughly chronological.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of John A. Ferrell were deposited with The Rockefeller Foundation Archives in 1967.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 29
Public health
- Desk Book - Index, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Desk Book - Annual Report, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Desk Book - County Appropriations, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Desk Book - International Health Commission (IHC) Executive Committee, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Desk Book - Expenditures, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Desk Book - Hookworm Film, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Desk Book - Interviews, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Desk Book - W. P. Jacocks, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Desk Book - Office Memoranda, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Desk Book - Office Rules, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Desk Book - Oklahoma, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Desk Book - Rockefeller Sanitary Commission, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Desk Book - State Directors Conference, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Index (Box 1, Folder 14)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Age of Health Officers (Box 1, Folder 15)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Child Hygiene (Box 1, Folder 16)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Completed Projects, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Cooperation with Administration (Box 1, Folder 18)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - County Health Departments (Box 1, Folder 19)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Discontinued Health Units (Box 1, Folder 20)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Expenditures in the U.S. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Expenditures for County Health Work, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Expenditures for County Health Work, 1910-1921 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Population Statistics, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Public Health Education, 1919-1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - Reprints (Box 1, Folder 26)
- International Health Division Statistics, 1910-1932 - State Health Services, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Diary Notes - United States, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Diary Notes - Canada, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Diary Notes - Mexico, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Diary Notes - Government Officials, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Diary Notes - Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- John A. Ferrell photographs, 1916-1944; 1018; 0.2 Cubic Feet; 2 folders and oversize; Approximately 30 prints
  Biographical / Historical
  John Atkinson Ferrell was born in Clinton, North Carolina, in December 1880. He received a B.S. from the University of North Carolina in 1902, an M.D. in 1907, and a Dr.P.H. from Johns Hopkins University in 1919.
  From 1902-1905 Dr. Ferrell taught school and was County Superintendent of Schools in Sampson County, North Carolina. In 1907 he became County Superintendent of Health there. From 1910-1913 Dr. Ferrell was associated with the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission and was State Director for North Carolina. In 1914 Dr. Ferrell became Associate Director of the International Health Division of The Rockefeller Foundation and served in that capacity until his retirement in 1944. Dr. Ferrell then became Medical Director of the Markle Foundation from 1944-1946. He was also Executive Secretary of the North Carolina Medical Care Commission from 1946-1957.
  Dr. Ferrell was a member of the American Medical Association, the Southern Medical Association, the National Malaria Committee of which he was Chairman in 1924, the Medical Society of the State of North Carolina for which he was Secretary from 1911-1914, the Medical Society of Wake County, North Carolina, the American Public Health Association of which he was President in 1933 and Chairman of the Board from 1935-1939. He was an honorary life member of the Conference of State and Provincial Health Authorities of North America and the Canadian Public Health Association.
  Dr. Ferrell's publications include: "Medical Inspection of Schools and School Children," 1912; "Careers in Public Health," 1923; "Trends in Preventative Medicine," 1923; "Malaria of the South," 1924; "Health in Relation to Citizenship," 1924; and "Survey of Provincial and State Organizations," 1927.
  Dr. Ferrell died in 1965.
  Photographs
  - John A. Ferrell, 1916-1944; Mounted on board, captions on back, several with severe yellowing, fading; 19 prints (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Scope and Contents note
    Rockefeller Foundation fellows, public health, Mexico, conferences, children, awards, ceremonies.
  - John A. Ferrell, 1916-1943; Mounted on board, captions on back, some fading, staining; 12 prints (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Diseases, typhus, conferences, Mexico, Brazil.
  - John A. Ferrell (Box 4)